<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Thoughts</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2020-04-10T00:06:48+02:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>apjd</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The electric flux density (displacement field)</title>
   <link href="/2020/04/09/electric-displacement-field"/>
   <updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2020/04/09/electric-displacement-field</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are some things that have caused a lot of confusion for me when I did electrodynamics, a lot of them spawn when matter comes into play. One of those things is the &lt;em&gt;electric displacement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In electrodynamics, &lt;em&gt;electric field strength&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;electric flux&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;electric flux density&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;magnetic field strength&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;magnetic flux&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;magnetic flux density&lt;/em&gt; are different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a &lt;strong&gt;fixed&lt;/strong&gt; positive charge somewhere in vacuum. It exerts a force on whatever charge we put into space. How do we know? We know this because we can measure an acceleration of the newly introduced charge. To be able to describe this force independent of how much charge we add to the space, we normalise this force and call it &lt;em&gt;electric field strength&lt;/em&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
\vec{E} = \frac{\vec{F}}{e}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direction of force &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{F}&lt;/script&gt; and thus of electric field strength &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; is defined from the postive charge to the negative charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what happens when we put matter somewhere into our space? It depends whether you have a conductor or a non-conductor. Conductors have free charges, non-conductors have fixed charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we put a conductor in a space with an electric field, the electric exerts forces on the freely movable charge in the conductor and they arrange such that they create an electric field of their own (internal electric field) which has the exactly opposite direction of the external electric field and exactly the same electric field strength. The sum of the external and internal electric field is zero, so there is no electric field inside the conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when we have a non-conductor? Here we have fixed charges. The external electric field causes the charges shift a little bit: electrical dipoles are induced! They are arranged such the they weaken the electrical field. Electrical dipoles are described mathematically by the electric dipole moment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{p} = e\vec{x}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; is how much positive charge the dipole has. The magnitude of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{x}&lt;/script&gt; is the distance between the positive and negative charge. &lt;strong&gt;The orientation of the dipole is defined from negative to positive (opposed to the electric field!)&lt;/strong&gt;. Now comes the confusion causer: &lt;strong&gt;The electric field and the induced electric moments have the same orientation! (this is important to know)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we define a macroscopic expression for the induced electric dipole moment: How much induced dipole moments per volume &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; do I have? (density of electric moments). This is called &lt;em&gt;polarisation&lt;/em&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{P} = \frac{\sum{p_i}}{V}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now back to the physics: As we see because of the movement of charges in conductors and shift of charges in non-conductors the electrical field strength outside of the material is always different from inside of the material:  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_{internal} \neq \vec{E}_{external}&lt;/script&gt;. In conductors: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_{internal} = 0&lt;/script&gt;, in non-conductors: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\vec{E}_{internal} &lt; \vec{E}_{external} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;. Is there any quantity whose value is independent of the material? Yes, the electric flux density &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{D}&lt;/script&gt;!:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{D} = \epsilon_0 \vec{E} + \vec{P}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confusion causer: with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; we now mean &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_{internal}&lt;/script&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;. Also note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt; have the same orientation! So somehow &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{D} \propto E_{external}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E_{external}&lt;/script&gt; is of course independent of the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confusion causer: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon_0 \vec{E}&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Please note that the electric displacement field is &lt;strong&gt;just a definition&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t try to overinterpret it &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon_0 \vec{E}&lt;/script&gt;. The internal electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_{internal}&lt;/script&gt; and the polarisation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt; are somehow added up together and result in a quantity which is independent of the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the intuition behind the electric displacement field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{D}&lt;/script&gt;? &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{D}&lt;/script&gt; is also called the &lt;em&gt;electric flux density&lt;/em&gt; with a unit of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{C}{m^2}&lt;/script&gt;. It is a measure of how many electric field lines per area we have: fields lines of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; and field lines of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt;. I think this is why we define the orientation of the dipoles from negative to positive: to be able to imagine &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{D}&lt;/script&gt; better (there is probably a more mathematical reason behind it, but I think like this unless something bad happens).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now want to have a look at the relationship between the internal electric field with the strength &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; and polarisation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt;. It should be like this: when the material is more polarised, the original external field in the material is more weakened so the internal field strength &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; decreases and vice versa. We can measure a proportionality constant between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt; (for linear materials):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \frac{\vec{P}}{\vec{E}} = \epsilon_0 \chi = \epsilon_0 (\epsilon_r - 1)
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon_r&lt;/script&gt; is the relative permeability (dimensionless) and somehow describes how “easily” one material gets polarised. Higher &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon_r&lt;/script&gt; means that the “portion” of the polarisation in the material is higher compared to the internal electrical field. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi&lt;/script&gt; is called the electric susceptibility and like &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon&lt;/script&gt; (they are more or less the same) how “easily” a material gets polarised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this equation we get a more simplified expression for the electric flux density (electric displacement field):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{D} = \epsilon_0 \vec{E} + \vec{P} =  \epsilon_0 \vec{E} + \epsilon_0 (\epsilon_r - 1) \vec{E} = \epsilon_0 \epsilon_r \vec{E}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally in real dielectric materials the polarisation does depend on orientation of the applied electric field because they are not completely symmetric. For example an electric field applied in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{x}&lt;/script&gt; direction may cause a higher density of dipoles (polarisation) than an electric field in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{y}&lt;/script&gt; direction. Also an electric field applied in one direction may cause in a polarisation with a different orientation. That’s why the electric susceptibility is generally a matrix: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi_{ij}&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  P_i = \epsilon_0 \sum_{j}{\chi_{ij} E_j}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we intuitively understand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi_{ij}&lt;/script&gt;? The first index &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; has always something to do with the result (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{P}&lt;/script&gt;). The second index &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt; has always something to do with the input (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt;). &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi_{21}&lt;/script&gt; for example describes the “influence” of the first component of the electric field (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E_x&lt;/script&gt;) on the second component of the polarisation (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_y&lt;/script&gt;). So for example if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi_{21}&lt;/script&gt; is non-zero and every other component of the matrix is zero we only get a polarisation if we apply an electric field in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{x}&lt;/script&gt; direction and the resulted polarisation is in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{y}&lt;/script&gt; direction (strange behaviour though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/capacitor.svg&quot; alt=&quot;capacitor&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Light and matter - A description based on a quantum mechanical two-level system and a classical electric field</title>
   <link href="/2020/04/06/light-matter-two-level-system"/>
   <updated>2020-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2020/04/06/light-matter-two-level-system</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the following we will describe the effect of light on matter based on a very simple two-level quantum mechanical system. In another post I will describe light classically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have a simple two-level quantum mechanical system with energies &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E_2&lt;/script&gt; and the states &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt;. Without any external influence, these two states are completely  uncoupled as there is no reason for a particle to jump from one state to the other (we assume the ground state as the initial state). This means that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt; are time-independent and are solutions to the time-independent Schrödinger equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \hat{H_0} \psi_j = E_j \psi_j
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what happens when light hits matter? The two states are now coupled! Why? Because now an electron in the ground state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; can absorb energy from light (a photon) and jump to the higher energy state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the calculations a bit simpler, we want to treat light classically. In classical electrodynamics, light is basically an alternating electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{B}&lt;/script&gt; field. For now we ignore the magnetic field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{B}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of the interaction of light and matter becomes: How does an alternating external electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; does change our two-level quantum mechanical system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the external electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; leads to a coupled two-level system because now a transition between the two states is possible. There is a general Ansatz for coupled quantum mechanical system: Describe the overall system as a linear combination of the uncoupled states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \psi = c_1 \psi_0 + c_2 \psi_1
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we are dealing with an alternating electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}(t)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_2&lt;/script&gt; must be time-independent. Because it can be that at a time the state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; is more “favourable” and at another time the state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An external electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt; can also lead to an induced dipole moment. Without the external field normally the dipole moment vanishes in time average because of the symmetry (imagine the probability cloud for the position of an electron around the core in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1s&lt;/script&gt; state in the hydrogen atom). This means that the overall energy of the system is now the sum of the energy of the unperturbed system and the dipole moment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \hat{H} = \hat{H_0} + \hat{H}_{dipole} = \hat{H_0} - e\hat{\vec{E}} \hat{x}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now has does the overall Schrödinger equation looks like? &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi&lt;/script&gt; must now be time-dependent, as the field changes the position probability clouds of the electron from time to time. So we need to solve the time-dependent Schrödinger equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  i\hbar \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial t} = (\hat{H_0} + \hat{H}_{dipole}) \psi
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what do we get for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi&lt;/script&gt; after solving the Schrödinger equation? &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt; are assumed to be known (solutions of the hydrogen atom). For &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_2&lt;/script&gt; we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  c_1 = \exp{\frac{-iE_1t}{\hbar}} \cos{\omega_{rabi} t}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  c_2 = \exp{\frac{-iE_2t}{\hbar}} \sin{\omega_{rabi} t}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  |c_1|^2 = \cos^2{(\omega_{rabi} t)}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  |c_2|^2 = \sin^2{(\omega_{rabi} t)}^2
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this means? As &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt; are time-independent, the time-dependence of the overall wave function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi&lt;/script&gt; is determined by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c_2&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means it that the electron jumps between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\psi_1&lt;/script&gt; with a frequency of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;2\omega_{rabi}&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1\omega_{rabi}&lt;/script&gt; is the frequency to see the electron in the same state again). This jumping back and forth of the electron is called the &lt;em&gt;Rabi oscillation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The the value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{Rabi}&lt;/script&gt; is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \omega_{Rabi} = \frac{\vec{E}_0 \cdot \vec{\mu}_{01}}{\hbar}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_0 \cdot \vec{\mu}_{01}&lt;/script&gt; is the energy gain that we get when the external electric field induces a dipole moment (please note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{Rabi}&lt;/script&gt; depends on the time-independent &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E}_0&lt;/script&gt;, so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{Rabi}&lt;/script&gt; is constant and only depends on the magnitude and direction of the external electric field and not its frequency. This makes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{Rabi}&lt;/script&gt; somehow characteristic to the material).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rabi-oscillation&quot;&gt;Rabi oscillation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when an electron jumps back and forth between two states? When it jumps to a higher energy state it absorbs energy (a photon). When is jumps back to the lower energy state it gives back the energy, it emits a photon. How many photons are emitted after the time &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;? Because the electron is in the ground state with a freqeuncy of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{rabi}&lt;/script&gt;, it emits &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{rabi} \times 2\pi \times t&lt;/script&gt; photons. What energy do the photons have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hbar \omega_{photon} = E_2 - E_1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physicists have a name for the phenomenon that an electron emits a photon after being excited to a higher state: &lt;em&gt;stimulated emission&lt;/em&gt; as it does not occur by itself and is induced by an external force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;damping&quot;&gt;Damping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real world we often cannot observe full Rabi oscillation, meaning we don’t see emission of the photons by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{rabi}&lt;/script&gt;. This is because electrons often lose their energy as heat before reaching a higher state. The probability of finding an electron in a higher states is given by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  |c_2|^2 \approx (\frac{\omega_{Rabi}}{2\gamma})^2
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is the damping constant. This means that if we want to have more electrons in higher states, we need higher &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_{Rabi}&lt;/script&gt;. This can be achieved by stronger external fields.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Light and atoms - A classical description, Lorentz Oscillator</title>
   <link href="/2020/04/06/light-atoms-classical-description"/>
   <updated>2020-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2020/04/06/light-atoms-classical-description</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How is the interaction of light and atoms described in classical physics? First we start defining light and matter in terms of classical physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classical electrodynamics, light is a wave. It is a wave of alternating electric and magnetic fields that are perpendicular to the direction of propagation and to each other. The electric and magnetic fields of light must be solutions to the electromagnetic wave equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \nabla^2 \vec{E} = \frac{1}{c^2} \frac{\partial^2 \vec{E}}{\partial t^2}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \nabla^2 \vec{B} = \frac{1}{c^2} \frac{\partial^2 \vec{B}}{\partial t^2}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; is the propagation speed. Every solution to the wave equation can be thought as a linear combination of many simple sinus waves with the same propagation speed &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;. So the must simple description of light is a sinus magnetic and a sinus electric field, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{E}(\vec{r}, t) = \vec{E}_0 \cos{(\vec{k} \cdot \vec{r} - \omega t)}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \vec{B}(\vec{r}, t) = \vec{B}_0 \cos{(\vec{k} \cdot \vec{r} - \omega t)}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{k}&lt;/script&gt; is the wave vector. It points to the direction of propagation and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\\|\overrightarrow{k}\\| = \dfrac{2\pi }{\lambda }&lt;/script&gt;. And there is actually a simple and nice relationship between the electric and magnetic field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \overrightarrow {B}=\dfrac {1}{\omega}\left( \overrightarrow {k}\times \overrightarrow {E}\right)
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the relationship between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{k}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega&lt;/script&gt;? Imagine a point fixed to a wave. How fast does it move? We now that after the time period &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; it covers a distance of the wavelength &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt;, so its effective speed is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  c=\dfrac {\lambda }{T}=\lambda \dfrac {1}{T}=\dfrac {2\pi }{\left| \overrightarrow {k}\right| }\dfrac {\omega }{2\pi }=\dfrac {\omega}{\left| \overrightarrow {k}\right| }
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here, if we imagine a point fixed to the wave, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;effective speed&lt;/em&gt; of the point. This speed is called the &lt;em&gt;phase velocity&lt;/em&gt;. As the point goes up and down, and not in straight line, its actual speed must be higher)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how can we describe an atom classically? Simple, as a positive and a negative charge connected by a spring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So classically, the interaction of light and matter becomes the interaction of a spring bounded dipole with an alternating electric field! The equation of motion of this system is simply that of the driven and damped harmonic oscillator, the Lorentz oscillator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
m_{e}\dfrac {\partial ^{2}}{\partial t^{2}}x \left( t\right) +m_{e  } \gamma \dfrac {\partial}{\partial t}x \left( t\right) +m_{e}{\omega}^{2}_{0}x\left( t\right) =-e\overrightarrow {E}_{0}e^{i\left( \overrightarrow {k}\overrightarrow {x}-\omega t\right) }
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is the damping constant. This considers possible energy losses in the atom. For the eigenfrequency &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_0&lt;/script&gt; we have: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_0 = \frac{\kappa}{m}&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; is the sprint constant). This is the frequency of the oscillation of the simple harmonic oscillator: if we don’t have damping and external drive forces. So &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_0&lt;/script&gt; is somehow “intrinsic” to the oscillator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution of the Lorentz oscillator for the distance between the electron the and core is given by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  x \left( t\right) =\overrightarrow {x}_{0}\left( t\right) e^{i( \overrightarrow {k}\overrightarrow {r}-\omega t + \phi)}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
{\vec{x}}_0 = \frac{-e\vec{E}_0}{m_e}\frac{1}{\sqrt{(\omega^2 - \omega_0^2)^2+ (\gamma \omega^2)}}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{equation}
  \tan{\phi} = \frac{\gamma \omega}{\omega_0^2 - \omega^2}
\end{equation}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean? When the frequency of the external electric field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega&lt;/script&gt; approaches the intrinsic frequency of the oscillator &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_0&lt;/script&gt; we get a higher and higher amplitude:  the distance between the electron and the core becomes larger and larger. Also we get a phase-shift between the external field and the oscillation of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\pi}{2}&lt;/script&gt; when &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega&lt;/script&gt; approaches &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega_0&lt;/script&gt; (look at these plots: amplitude against &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega/\omega_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi&lt;/script&gt; against &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega/\omega_0&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The coupling of states in quantum mechanics</title>
   <link href="/2020/04/06/coupling-states-quantum-mechanics"/>
   <updated>2020-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2020/04/06/coupling-states-quantum-mechanics</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Consider a simple quantum mechanical system consisting of two eigenstates &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ket{0}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ket{1}&lt;/script&gt;. A coupling between these two states means that there is a non-zero probability of a particle to go from one state to the other. Physically a coupling between two states is always achieved only by external influences. For example, light can couple different states in an atom. An electron can absorb a photon and go to a higher energy state, thus we can say these two states are coupled by the photon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally there are some physical quantity changes associated with such a transition. In simple terms: when a particle goes from one state to another state, something is changed. For example in case of photon absorption the energy of the electron will increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we calculate such changes in physical quantities in quantum mechanics? Let’s consider the energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally the Hamiltonian can be written as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H_{fi} = \left&lt; f \middle| \hat{H} \middle| i \right&gt; %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f \ne i&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_{fi}&lt;/script&gt; is the energy difference between the final state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ket{f}&lt;/script&gt; and the initial state &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ket{i}&lt;/script&gt;. The sign of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_{fi}&lt;/script&gt; determines the energy gain or loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_{fi}&lt;/script&gt; can be calculated by an integral:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H_{fi} = \left&lt; f \middle| \hat{H} \middle| i \right&gt; = \int{\psi_f^* \hat{H} \psi_i dx} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The use of exponential functions in everyday life</title>
   <link href="/2020/04/05/importance-of-exponential-functions"/>
   <updated>2020-04-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2020/04/05/importance-of-exponential-functions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exponential functions are an important class of mathematical functions. Generally they are defined as the solutions of the following differential equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{df(t)}{dt} = C f(t)&lt;/script&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; is a constant and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt; is a variable, for example time. This means that exponential functions describe situations where the rate of change of something depends on how much of that something is currently available. The rate of change basically answers the question: How many new things do I get after a specific time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example is the spreading of a contagious disease. The number of people that get sick after a certain period of time, for example after one day, depends on how many people already have the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the growth of money due to the interest rate. The amount of money that is added to my money after one year depends on how much money I already have in my bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
